<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>ninly’s bog</title><link href="http://ninly.github.io/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="http://ninly.github.io/feeds/tag/commonplacing.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>http://ninly.github.io/</id><updated>2015-02-13T00:00:00-06:00</updated><entry><title>The Notebook as Database: John Locke, Commonplacing, and Hash Functions</title><link href="http://ninly.github.io/posts/2015/02/the-notebook-as-database/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2015-02-13T00:00:00-06:00</updated><author><name>ninly</name></author><id>tag:ninly.github.io,2015-02-13:posts/2015/02/the-notebook-as-database/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;A couple of months ago I stumbled by happy accident onto the topic of
&lt;em&gt;keeping a commonplace book&lt;/em&gt;, or &lt;em&gt;commonplacing&lt;/em&gt;. While this did call up
vague memories of reading about commonplace books in my earlier life as
a Humanities student, I had fully appreciated neither its power as a
tool for memory and worldview-organization nor (and more to the point
here) its kinship with a host of techniques used today for organizing
large bodies of data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="commonplace-books"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Commonplace Books&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are not familiar with the reading practices of the Renaissance
and the early modern periods, a &lt;em&gt;commonplace book&lt;/em&gt; is essentially a
notebook, kept by habitual readers, for hand-copying quotations from
their reading. Such quotations are entered under headings -- the &amp;quot;common
places&amp;quot; (the word comes from &lt;em&gt;locis communis&lt;/em&gt; in Latin, or &lt;em&gt;topos
koinos&lt;/em&gt; in Greek, and the technique descends from the copybooks used in
studying those languages) -- that in Renaissance/Enlightenment practice
were governed in part by the worldview of the day. Later on, as literacy
spread to greater populations, the practice morphed toward something
more like the modern scrapbook.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a rich and varied topic; much has been written about
commonplacing as a technique for interacting with one's reading and, as
I suggested above, organizing a worldview within a cultural context. As
introduced by William H. Sherman:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
Renaissance readers, writers, and speakers were well-trained in
textual recycling, and one of their most powerful and pervasive
tools was the ‘commonplace book’ - a collection of notes from
reading and other sources that the compiler might want to recall,
and reuse, at a later date. While the structure and purpose of these
volumes varied enormously, they were distinguished from random
collections of quotations (in theory, at least) by being gathered
under conventional headings called loci communes or ‘common places’.
As Ann Moss has explained, &amp;quot;The more elementary
commonplace-books ... would be divided into sections under heads listing
the main virtues and vices, and all their subsidiary manifestations.
More advanced commonplace-books might have ambitious programmes for
covering all knowledge, or they might be specialist repertories of
excerpts relevant to specific disciplines&amp;quot; (&lt;em&gt;Printed
Commonplace-Books and the Structuring of Renaissance Thought&lt;/em&gt;,
Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1996, v). The headings could be tailored to
an individual’s personal or professional needs, suggested by
teachers, or bought in blank-books with printed headings and
decorative borders - and readers who did not have the patience or
the resources to gather their own entries could even buy a book with
the quotations already printed or written in. &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.ampltd.co.uk/collections_az/RenCpbks-BL/editorial-introduction.aspx"&gt;[source]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://3stages.org/quotes/cpb.html"&gt;Here are some other quotations&lt;/a&gt;
about commonplace books -- a web search will turn up much more if you're
interested in the historical context and practice. The noteworthy part
for me here is the notion that the technique was a practice -- a
technology -- related to &lt;em&gt;memory&lt;/em&gt;, an early-modern &lt;em&gt;ars memorativa&lt;/em&gt;,
even. The &amp;quot;commonplacer&amp;quot; keeps notes for later review and use,
whether to deploy in one's own writing (in a day when authoritative
quotation had a completely different quality and import than it has
today) or for organizing one's personal reception and perception of
significant ideas, also to be reviewed when musing on one's development.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This practice grew in the early days of print media and (more)
widespread literacy, when the proliferation of text would have been as
daunting as it was exciting to an avid reader (of course, cf.  parallels
with today's networked explosion of content and its attendant meta- and
big data). Agile readers used whatever methods they might devise or find
available to keep track and make sense of their reading amid this
proliferation of text and idea, in hopes that they could dredge it up
when the reference was needed, and possibly even keep their heads above
water in making personal sense out of so much information.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Essentially, it was a technique for &lt;em&gt;cataloging&lt;/em&gt; information that has made
a personal impression.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="locke-s-hash-function"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Locke's hash function&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All of this sort of caught my imagination because when I learned about how
and why commonplace books were kept, I kept thinking of the whole thing
as like a &amp;quot;manual database&amp;quot; for personal reading.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With that in mind, I learned that the practice of commonplacing was
stoked when, in 1685, Enlightenment thinker John Locke published a
method he had devised for organizing entries in his own commonplace
books. Essentially, he added a technique of &lt;em&gt;indexing&lt;/em&gt; to the
&lt;em&gt;cataloging&lt;/em&gt; that was already inherent in commonplacing technique. But
because a commonplace book is (a) a physical book, and (b) essentially a
work-in-progress, its headings chosen on the fly as one cleaves headlong
through a sea of text, preparing one's commonplace notebook presented a
challenge -- one didn't know in advance precisely what ideas would be
making an impression, and thus what headings would be needed, without
taking a shot in the dark.  Some did try -- presuming that their copying
would fit into a religiously or philosophically determined rubric.
There is more interesting history here, but I'll not delve into it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Locke's method cinched my comparison with a database: he basically
invented a rudimentary hash function, and put a hash table in the front
matter of his notebook. &lt;em&gt;Et voilà&lt;/em&gt;, the notebook as database!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm not familiar enough with the history of cataloging or information
and organization to know if this had any direct precursors or cousins in
contemporary practice, but I've been on the lookout for similar
organizational practices, or other ideas that prefigured the modern hash
function in the predigital world. Let me know if you know of anything.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Locke's method is described in some detail &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.historyofinformation.com/expanded.php?id=3744"&gt;here with quotations from Locke&lt;/a&gt;
himself. See also this &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://pds.lib.harvard.edu/pds/view/13925922"&gt;facsimile and transcription&lt;/a&gt;
of the book where his method was originally published. I'm calling the
hashing part of his method the &lt;em&gt;Lockean hash&lt;/em&gt;, and in short, this is how
it works:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Given a commonplace heading (Locke calls it a Head, and his example is
'Epistle'),&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol class="arabic simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Take the first letter of the heading (e.g. &lt;em&gt;Epistle&lt;/em&gt; -&amp;gt; &lt;strong&gt;E&lt;/strong&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Append to it the &lt;em&gt;next&lt;/em&gt; vowel that occurs in the heading (e.g. &lt;em&gt;Epistle&lt;/em&gt; -&amp;gt; &lt;strong&gt;Ei&lt;/strong&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If the word begins with a vowel but does not contain a subsequent
vowel, double the initial (e.g. &lt;em&gt;Arts&lt;/em&gt; -&amp;gt; &lt;strong&gt;Aa&lt;/strong&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Other cases are not covered, and because this isn't a comprehensive
algorithm for an automated system, that would not cause much difficulty
in the overall use case. The main exception I can think of -- a word
with all consonants -- would probably never have been encountered (this
was before the ubiquity of acronyms, after all). Many people would
probably have organized their notes under Latin headings, too (Locke
specifically recommends keeping it to &lt;em&gt;one&lt;/em&gt; language, an amusing hint at
the kind of organizational challenges his scholarly contemporaries
faced).  Notably, &lt;em&gt;y&lt;/em&gt;-as-a-vowel is not handled.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But here we are, with a number of &amp;quot;hash buckets&amp;quot; equal to the number of
word-initial letters used, times five vowels.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For Locke's own notebook (in part because orthography was just
different, and possibly Latin, in those days) he omitted/merged a few
initials -- J and I, for instance, share a bucket in his system --
bringing the number of potential initials down to 20. This enabled Locke
to construct a convenient 4X5 grid of initial letters which, when folded
with the 5 vowels, rendered a 100-slot hash space. Locke describes using
black and red lead to draw the resulting table in the beginning of his
notebook which, along with a few additional techniques for pagination
and pageflow, would serve as &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://idmaa.org/wp-content/uploads/2013/03/Brian-J.-McNely-2.jpg"&gt;its index&lt;/a&gt;,
much as a hash table does in database or other software. (Note that this
page is from a &lt;em&gt;printed&lt;/em&gt; book explaining and illustrating how he did it,
whereas the technique itself was a manual one.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When a heading is added to the notebook to accommodate new quotations or
notes, it would be hashed (mentally) and the page number of the copy
would be added to the corresponding slot in the hash table. Before
creating a new heading, Locke would consult his index to see if he had
already begun an page under that hash, and if so the copy would go there
instead. Upon filling a spread, Locke would continue copying not on the
next page (which might already have content), but on the &lt;em&gt;next blank
spread&lt;/em&gt;, adding references to the new page number to the bottom of the
just-filled page &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; to the front-matter index. By allowing headings
to leapfrog each other, this method both minimizes page waste and tends
to keep newer and more active material closer the last-filled pages of
the book.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="analysis-of-the-hash-function"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Analysis of the Hash Function&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I discovered and researched all of this with consideration of making a
commonplace book for my own use, and I wondered if Locke's method would
work for me as effectively as it did for many in the 18th century.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Granted, by standards of today's usage of hash functions, Locke's is
beyond rudimentary. It has a grossly nonuniform distribution (being
lashed to natural-language letter frequencies), and is thus riddled with
the likelihood of collisions (see further analysis below). But it has an
interesting property that no passable modern hash has (or needs): it is
&lt;em&gt;intuitive&lt;/em&gt;. That is to say, Locke (or anyone who used a similar method)
might run across an interesting idea about algorithms, and think &amp;quot;Hmm,
&lt;em&gt;Algorithms&lt;/em&gt;...  &lt;strong&gt;A&lt;/strong&gt;... (&lt;em&gt;l&lt;/em&gt;...  &lt;em&gt;g&lt;/em&gt;...) &lt;strong&gt;o&lt;/strong&gt;...&amp;quot; and immediately
look up all the pages in his notebook where he or she might have copied
or taken notes under &lt;em&gt;Algorithms&lt;/em&gt;. Certainly, those entries might be
interspersed with entries about &lt;em&gt;Arrows&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Atomism&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Astronomy&lt;/em&gt;, and
any other headings that hash to &lt;strong&gt;Ao&lt;/strong&gt;, but barring a terribly unlucky
distribution of headwords, this does not seem like a major issue for a
notebook-sized repository. It may even be considered a feature, if
maintaining a commonplace book is also seen as an opportunity to make
unexpected connections or explore and reflect on one's passage through
reading.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="further-analysis"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Further Analysis&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To get a sense of how bad Locke's hash distribution really is, I wrote
some code to hash an input list of words and keep track of the hash
table for some simple analysis. I then fed it a list of the &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/first20hours/google-10000-english"&gt;10,000 most
commonly used words&lt;/a&gt; per Google
n-grams -- which is admittedly probably not representative of words
likely to end up as headings in someone's commonplace book.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here's a histogram of the distribution (made using bitly's sweet little
&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://github.com/bitly/data_hacks"&gt;data_hacks&lt;/a&gt; commandline tools), with the 100 slots divided into 20 bins:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="literal-block"&gt;
$ cat data.txt | histogram.py --buckets=20
# NumSamples = 100; Min = 0.00; Max = 505.00
# Mean = 96.590000; Variance = 6119.221900; SD = 78.225456; Median
# 85.000000
# each * represents a count of 1
    0.0000 -    25.2500 [    13]: *************
   25.2500 -    50.5000 [    16]: ****************
   50.5000 -    75.7500 [    19]: *******************
   75.7500 -   101.0000 [    16]: ****************
  101.0000 -   126.2500 [    10]: **********
  126.2500 -   151.5000 [     5]: *****
  151.5000 -   176.7500 [    11]: ***********
  176.7500 -   202.0000 [     2]: **
  202.0000 -   227.2500 [     3]: ***
  227.2500 -   252.5000 [     0]:
  252.5000 -   277.7500 [     3]: ***
  277.7500 -   303.0000 [     0]:
  303.0000 -   328.2500 [     0]:
  328.2500 -   353.5000 [     0]:
  353.5000 -   378.7500 [     1]: *
  378.7500 -   404.0000 [     0]:
  404.0000 -   429.2500 [     0]:
  429.2500 -   454.5000 [     0]:
  454.5000 -   479.7500 [     0]:
  479.7500 -   505.0000 [     1]: *
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is clearly nowhere near a uniform distribution. Here's a bar graph
showing where the headings land in the hash table (the hashes are
plotted in alphabetical order):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="Lockean Hash Distribution of 10,000 Common Words" src="images/2015-02-13_locke_index_bar.png" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's hard to see the tick labels in that image, but the &lt;strong&gt;Co&lt;/strong&gt; and
&lt;strong&gt;Re&lt;/strong&gt; hashes are by far the most used (this also accounts for the long
tail on the histogram above). Significant showings are also made by
&lt;strong&gt;Se&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;Ca&lt;/strong&gt;, and &lt;strong&gt;Po&lt;/strong&gt; (with more the 250 occurrences apiece),
followed by &lt;strong&gt;De&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;Pa&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;Sa&lt;/strong&gt; (with over 200 occurrences).
Notice also that several of the &lt;strong&gt;X&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;Z&lt;/strong&gt; hashes have fewer than 5
occurrences -- not a huge surprise for English words. &lt;strong&gt;Zu&lt;/strong&gt; gets
some love, but that's because &lt;strong&gt;Z&lt;/strong&gt; is merged with &lt;strong&gt;Q&lt;/strong&gt;, so all the
Qu-words land in that bucket.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="stay-tuned"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Stay tuned...&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A few ideas, none of them new, to take away from all this exploration:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol class="arabic simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Commonplacing is an interesting technique, possibly worth
reconsidering for personal use.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;John Locke was kind of cool, and had influential ideas that turn up in
unexpected places.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The organization and navigation of wildly proliferating content in
the Renaiassance gave rise to solutions that prefigure some modern
ones, including fixtures of computer science such as string hashing
and databases.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a future post I hope to present a bit more analysis and exploration
of Locke's function, offer some tweaks to improve its distribution, and
reflect on my own experience with a commonplace book. I'll also try to
clean up my hash-analysis code to share. Until then, agile reading!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</summary><category term="algorithms"></category><category term="hashing"></category><category term="commonplacing"></category></entry></feed>