<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>ninly’s bog</title><link href="http://ninly.github.io/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="http://ninly.github.io/feeds/tag/eudyptula.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>http://ninly.github.io/</id><updated>2014-03-28T22:10:00-05:00</updated><entry><title>Taking the Eudyptula Challenge</title><link href="http://ninly.github.io/posts/2014/03/eudyptula-challenge/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-03-28T22:10:00-05:00</updated><author><name>ninly</name></author><id>tag:ninly.github.io,2014-03-28:posts/2014/03/eudyptula-challenge/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;It wasn't so long ago that I was pounding away on my Matasano Challenge
code, and thinking about how I might write about the progress I was
making. It was abstract, though -- progress to be sure, but a lot of
the kind of thing you seem to learn when looking back at code you keyed
several months prior. Painful in some ways, enlightening study in
others.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I had already been distracted once, hence the several months. Somewhere
in the midst of a &lt;em&gt;real&lt;/em&gt; course I had to take in a &lt;em&gt;real&lt;/em&gt; school
(Matasano's efforts and organization are real, of course, but I didn't
have to pay them money or depend on a certain grade for economic
reasons) and the crush of raising a couple of infants who don't know
a whole lot about cryptography or programming, my code fell to the
wayside. I still hope to get back to it one day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But something else happened recently, even as I was starting
to delve back into the Matasano stuff. A &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://eudyptula-challenge.org/"&gt;new challenge&lt;/a&gt;, modeled on Matasano's approach, but
geared toward Linux kernel hacking and many of the practical intricacies
involved with the Linux kernel workflow: coding style, patch submission,
and so on, as well as the long slog of learning how an operating system
actually &lt;em&gt;works&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I found out about Eudyptula last month and signed right up. My free time
has been wrapped around that axle ever since. Unfortunately, that means
I'm not investing time in active FOSS projects or code I can share,
which was a thing with Matasano, too. But I'm working on a foundation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm still fascinated with cryptography, both practical and theoretical,
and the kinds of tasks that Matasano was throwing at me were also
especially useful in getting my head around some day-to-day code
organization and workflow. But &lt;em&gt;system programming&lt;/em&gt; has always been a
deeper interest of mine than some of the common learn-to-code tutorial
stuff out there these days. My day job involves embedded systems and
their designers, too, and I always had a strong inpulse for at least
the idea of actually &lt;em&gt;developing&lt;/em&gt; the kinds of real-time systems I
test and troubleshoot. But learning the low level has often felt
pretty slow-going, and I haven't found a whole lot of programmatic,
goal-oriented guidance. Eudyptula's little penguin seems, so far, to be
providing just what I needed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That's not to say he's making it &lt;em&gt;easy&lt;/em&gt;; it's still slow-going. But
that's because the Linux kernel is massive and mindbogglingly complex.
There's a sense of &lt;em&gt;progress&lt;/em&gt;, though, of what to read next, of what I'm
missing. And #kernelnewbies (an IRC channel) is providing a good amount
of assistance and perspective, too. There is a sense of goal in it all,
too: The introductory email in the series suggests that after completing
the exercises one should be equipped, if not to &lt;em&gt;be&lt;/em&gt; a kernel subsystem
maintainer (heavens forbid!), at least to understand what the heck it is
they do, and to be an active developer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And in addition to all that personal practical coolness, we're talking
about the Linux kernel: one of the most significant collaborative
efforts in the history of cooperation. Perplexing at times, not without
its barbs and pitfalls, but an effective sort of juggernaut that we all
use and benefit from every day, whether or not we know it or think about
it. And in its own interest of longevity, that juggernaut has produced
this little spinoff; it's pretty exciting to be plugged into that.&lt;/p&gt;
</summary><category term="linux-kernel"></category><category term="eudyptula"></category></entry></feed>